Garemani Family Collection of Persian and Arabic Manuscripts and Books LSC.0453
UCLA Library Special Collections
Garemani Family collection of Persian and Arabic manuscripts and books
circa 1514-1899
UCLA Library Special Collections
LSC.0453
1.5 Linear Feet (3 boxes)
The collection consists of Persian and Arabic printed works and manuscripts dating from approximately 1514-1899. Subjects include history, literature, medicine, mathematics, diplomatics, theology, and poetry.
Restrictions on Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Provenance/Source of Acquisition
Gift of Noyan and Homa Garemani, 2004.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9953992723606533
Scope and Content
The collection consists of nineteen Iranian manuscripts and three rare printed works, dating from the late Safawid to the late Qajar periods. The subjects of the items vary from science and medicine to history, literature, religion, and grammar. Of particular scholarly interest is a rare Persian translation of an unidentified Turkish commentary on Maulana Jalal al-Din Rumi's Maṣnavῑ, and an original Persian-language biography on Napolean Bonaparte. Published works have been included in the finding aid; in addition, full catalog records for these books can be found in the UCLA Library online catalog by performing a keyword search on the phrase, "Noyan Garemani collection" in the UCLA Library catalog.
Organization and Arrangement
Arranged in the following series:
Books, 1873-1911 (Box 1).
Manuscripts, ca. 1514-1899 (Boxes 1-3).
Civilization, Arab -- Archives.; Manuscripts.; Arabic literature -- 1801 -- Archives.; Arabic literature -- 1258-1800 -- Archives.; Jalal al-Din Rumi, Maulana
- Books, 1873-1911
  - To the high and mighty sovereign, the Shah of Persia ... [Hertford, England: Stephen Austin and Sons, Printers, 1873]. (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Scope and Content
    Correspondent: Anglo-Jewish Association.
    Physical Description: 1 item.
    Physical Description: Bound in red morocco, with gilt edges.
    Scope and Content Note Petition to the Shah of Persia by the Anglo Jewish Association, requesting "an equal measure of justice to all ... subjects" on behalf of the Jews of Persia.
  - [Tehran]: Dar karkhana-I ustad ?aj ?Abd al-Ra?im ?urat al-?iba paziruft, 1335 [1911]. (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Scope and Contents
    Correspondent: Munsha ?at-I Mi?bah. Kitab-I munsha ?at-I Mi?bah.
    Scope and Content Note Letter-writing manual, in Persian. Quarter blue cloth, brown marbled wrappers over boards. Inscribed in Persian on front endpapers: "This book belongs to Mahdi Ma?rashi." With the stamp of the Ministery of Cultural Affairs.
  - The bronze statue, or, The virgin's kiss = Bushe-yi ?a?o?a ([Tehran]: Dar al-?ibaa-I Farus, 1326 [1908]). (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Correspondent: Reynolds, George W. M. (George William MacArthur). Physical Description: 1 item.
    Scope and Content Note Rare Persian translation of Reynold's, The bronze statue.
- Manuscripts, ca. 1514-1899
  - 1 Risalah dar fann-i ?ibb (Treatise in the art of medicine)., 1804 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Author: ?Ali al-Ri?a ibn Musá, d. 818 or 19.
    Physical Description: 64 leaves: paper; 164 x 103 mm. bound to 164 x 107 mm.
    Scope and Content Note Interlinear Persian translation of a treatise on medicine by the eighth Shiite Imam ?Ali al-Ri?a ibn Musá. It is also known as Risalah al-dhahabiyah, or "The golden." The translator's name is Mu?ammad ibn al-?asan al-Mashhadi (possibly also the scribe). The content covers a variety of diseases and the cures, and develops a theory of physiognomy. The body is compared to a kingdom whose king is the soul, and the agents of the king are the limbs and the veins. The home of the king is the heart; and his treasury, the intestine and the stomach. The text recommends good food and drink to maintain health and cure ailments. The manuscript also discusses the four humors, general hygiene, and recommendations for sleep and brushing teeth. The manuscript concludes with a summary of the stages of life (the final stage beginning at age forty), and rules for bathing, bowel movements, traveling, and copulation.
    Layout: Average of 16 lines of text per page.
    Script: Naskh.
    Binding: Stiff red leather, with brown leather spine.
    Additional descriptive data: Arabic terms and phrases in blue, Persian text in black; marginalia in several hands.
    Text in Arabic and Persian.
  - 2 Atishkadah Fire altar., 1804-1805 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Author: [Bafqi, Mu?ammad Mufid ibn Ma?mud, 17th cent.]
    Scribe: Aman Allah ibn Mu?ammad Taqi [Zanganah?] Na?ir.
    Physical Description: 66 leaves: paper; 175 x 105 mm. bound to 178 x 111 mm.
    Origin: Qajar Iran.
    Scope and Content Note A?ar Baygdili's anthology of several hundred Persian poets from all regions of Iran and present-day Afganistan. This version is contemporary with the third-oldest manuscript used by ?asan Sadat Na?iri in his 1958-1962 partial critical edition.
    Contents:
    * ff. 1b-5b: Opening and table of contents. * ff. 5b-179b: First censer: older poets. * ff. 5b-14a: First flame: poetry of kings. * ff. 14a-151b: First ember: the poets of Iran. * ff. 14a-28b: First flare: Azerbayjan. * ff. 28b-77b: Second flare: Khurasan. * ff. 77b-85b: Third flare: Caspian region. * ff. 85b-132b: Fourth flare: the two Iraqs. * ff. 85b-86a: First ray: Persian poetry of Arab Iraq. * ff. 86a-132b: Second ray: Persian poetry of Persian Iraq. * ff. 132b-151b: Fifth flare: Fars. * ff. 151b-175a: Second Ember: the poets of Turan. * ff. 175a-177b: Third Ember: the poets of India (Deccan, Delhi, and Kashmir). * ff. 177b-179b: Light: the poetesses. * ff. 179b-239a: Second censer: contemporary poets. * ff. 179b-215a: First beam: contemporaries of the author. * ff. 215a-239a: Second beam: the author.
    Layout: 25 lines of text per page.
    Script: Nasta? liq.
    Binding: Black leather blind stamped binding.
    Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink with headings in red. Occasional staining. Notes in pencil and ink, in several hands, on pastedowns and endpapers.
    Text in Persian.
  - 3 Jam?-I Mufidi mujallid-i siyyum The third volume of the beneficial collection., 1860 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Scope and Content Note Selection from Bafqi's Jam?-I Mufidi (History of Yazd, or Iran), consisting of a biography of 14th century Shiite Sufi master Ni ?mat Allah Vali. In the introduction, Bafqi states that he consulted a number of contemporary texts on his subject (f. 5). The narrative begins with the master's birth in Aleppo, and then relates his travels, pilgrimages, encounters with important personages, and arrival in the city of Kirman (f. 23a). The biography concludes with a lengthy list of the central figures of the order, following Ni ?mat Allah Vali's death. The last date mentioned in the text is 1655 December 12, well within the author's lifetime.
    Layout: 15 lines of text per page.
    Binding: Soft dark green leather, blind stamped.
    Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink with headings, or the first few words of each section, in red.
  - 4 [Biography of Napoleon Bonaparte]., [ca. 1808?] (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Physical Description: 79 leaves: paper; 214 x 160 mm. bound to 217 x 165 mm.
    Scope and Content Note Original biographical composition on Napoleon Bonaparte; possibly incomplete, or lacking pages towards the end. Continuous narrative, without chapter divisions, except for three breaks on 38a, 39b, and 60b. After each break the author writes "thus says the author" or "the narrator narrates," thereafter resuming his story. The author refers to his subject as "General Napoleon," and the last dated reference is 1796. However, the biography was clearly composed at a later date, as author mentions an event which occurred in 1808 (f. 25a), when Bonaparte was First Consul and Emperor of France. The historical context for this biography reflects the political and nationalistic tensions during the reign of King Fat?-?Ali Shah Qajar (r. 1797-1834), who courted the French for military assistance to offset the Russian threat to the north, and the British expansion in India and modern Afghanistan in the east and southeast.
    Layout: Average 21 lines of text per page (in columns).
    Decoration: First two pages gilt.
    Binding: Soft black leather.
    Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, framed in a red, gold, and blue border. Occasional stains and smears.
  - 5 ?Ayn al-bakka? Weeper's eye., [18--] (Box 2, Folder 2)
    Author: Burujirdi, Sayyid ?Ali Naqi.
    Scribe: Mu?ammad ?usayn ibn Mu?ammad Ja? far.
    Physical Description: 263 leaves: paper; 210 x 130 mm. bound to 210 x 136 mm.
    Origin: Iran/Iraq.
    Scope and Content Note Collection of stories about the death or martyrdom of Shiite holy figures, with special emphasis on the events surrounding the death of the third Imam, ?usayn ibn ?Ali (see Storey I, p. 219). The manuscript immediately opens with a narrative, instead of the typical introductory paragraphs. It begins with ?usayn's march from Medina towards Kufa, where he was met by an opposing army, followed by an account of the martyrdom of several of his companions. This section also tells the story of Za? far the genie, who volunteers to die for the Imam. Next, ?usayn gives the final speech to his family before the 10th of Mu?arram (the day of his martyrdom), and the author includes accounts of the deaths of ?usayn's grandfather (the prophet Mu?ammad), mother (Fa?ima ?ahra?, Mu?ammad's daughter), and father (Imam ?Ali). The narrative shortly reverts to the martyrdom of the eighth Imam (?Ali al-Ri?a) before returning to the subject of ?usayn, specifically ?usayn's severed head, which prompts fantastic occurrences en route to Syria. The manuscript also covers the battle of ?iffin, where ?usayn's father ?Ali had been betrayed by his companions; it then diverts to the story of Abraham's near sacrifice of Ishmael (as opposed to Isaac, in Genesis). The author concludes with accounts of the martyrdom of ?usayn's other male relatives.
    Layout: 14 lines of text per page.
    Binding: Brown leather, blind stamped; light blue pastedowns.
    Additional descriptive data: Chapter headings and punctuations in red ink, text in black. The text is bordered by a red box for the first eight leaves; the final chapter headings are blank.
  - 6 [Correspondence, et. al]., [ca. 1827?] (Box 2, Folder 3)
    Physical Description: 56 leaves: paper; 278 x 189 mm. bound to 280 x 193 mm.
    Scope and Content Note Persian translation of a draft report on the province of ?Iraq-I ?Ajam (in modern-day central and western Iran), and copies of translated correspondence between the Qajar ruling elite and various European powers, especially Imperial Russia. In 1826, Russia had defeated the Qajars a second time, and annexed additional territory in the Caucasus. Fat? ?Ali Shah was rumored to harbor plans to construct a city in the province of ?Iraq-I ?Ajam, as the road between Azerbayjan and the capital Tehran was unprotected. The correspondence, report, and assorted documents probably relate to these events, as the scribe dedicates the manuscript to Fat? ?Ali Shah Qajar (r. 1797-1834) and writes that the people of Iran have been subjected to much cruelty of late. The last letter is dated 1827 January 6.
    * ff. 1b-4b: Opening. * ff. 4b-13b: Provincial survey of ?Iraq-I ?Ajam. * ff. 13b-18a: Blank. * ff. 18a-36b: Translation of papers documenting diplomatic exchange with Britain (1823 November 20). * ff. 37a-39a: Blank. * ff. 39a-44b: Correspondence documenting Russian and Austrian affairs. * ff. 45a-46a: Blank. * ff. 46b-50a: Correspondence documenting Russian and French affairs (some written by Qajar official in Istanbul). * ff. 50b-51a: Blank. * ff. 51b-56a: Report of diplomatic mission to Istanbul.
    Layout: 12 lines of text per page.
    Binding: Soft green leather.
    Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, except for the geographical indicators in the report, which are in red. Occasional staining and separation of leaves.
  - 7 Mirqat al-?u? ud fi taw?id al-wujud Ladder of ascension in the unity of existence., 1879 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    Author: Imam-i Jum?a, al-?aj Mulla Mu?ammad ?Ali.
    Scribe: ?Abd Allah Tabrizi Qazvini.
    Physical Description: 65 leaves: paper; 180 x 101 mm. bound to 165 x 111 mm.
    Scope and Content Note Religio-philosophical treatise. Each section discusses a theme, or an exegesis, on verses from the Koran or Hadith. The author begins by rebuking those who see only appearances, followers of opinions and whims; thus establishing the binary opposition of appearance/essence. Manuscript includes several sections on desire, followed by relevant exegetical passages. Also contains numerous discussions on aspects of the soul.
    Binding: Bound in cats-paw calf, stamped in gilt, with marbled endpapers. The text block is entirely detached from its binding, and extends 15 milimeters above the top of the boards.
    Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, with occasional page stains. Sparse marginalia, including a few Russian notations in pencil.
  - 8 al-?Awamil fi al-na?w The elements of grammar., 1824 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    Author: Jurjanii, ?Abd al-Qahir ibn ?Abd al-Ra?man, d. 1078?
    Physical Description: 27 leaves: paper; 215 x 164 mm. bound to 217 x 165 mm.
    Scope and Content Note Jurjani's 11th century grammatical treatise on Arabic, ?Awamil al-mi ?ah. A second title, written in red ink on f. 1b, reads "hadha kit?b al-?awamil al-Jurjani," or "this is Jurjani's book of elements." The manuscript begins with divisions of words into "sound and sense," or pronunciation and meaning. The concept of "sound" is further subdivided into acoustic and modal categories; the first consisting of 91 additional subdivisions, and the second, 7. These subdivisions, plus the two major divisions of sense or meaning, add up to Jurjani's one hundred elements of grammar.
    Binding: Soft black leather, blind stamped, with golden paper pastdowns.
    Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink on blue paper, with some headings and underlining in red, and extensive marginalia. Occasional staining and holes.
    Text in Arabic.
  - 9 [Divan-i Manuchihri Damghani] [Poems of Manuchihri Damghani]., 1866 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    Author: [Manuchihri Damghani, Abu Najm Mirza Ma?mud Hakim.
    Scribe: A?mad ibn Qaw?].
    Physical Description: 34 leaves: paper; 208 x 125 mm. bound to 210 x 130 mm.
    Scope and Content Note Selected poetry by 11th century Persian poet Manuchihri Damghani. The manuscript contains six of Manuchihri Damghani's "qa?idas," panegyrics to the Ghaznawid dynasty court elite, and a number of "tarji? bands," poems with refrain.
    Layout: Average 13 lines of text per page.
    Binding: Soft brown leather, blind stamped.
    Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink on blue paper. ff. 30-34 are stained.
  - 10 [Siraj al-munir, va Divan-i Sabzavari] [The luminous light beam, and Poems of Sabzavari]., 1866 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    Author: Mu?ammad Sharif ibn Shams al-Din Mu?ammad; Sabzavari, Hadi ibn Mahdi, b. 1797 or 8.
    Scribe: ?afi? ibn ?Abd al-Karim al-?Aqili al-Kirmani.
    Physical Description: 130 leaves: paper; 117 x 110 mm. bound to 181 x 115 mm.
    Scope and Content Note The manuscript contains two works. Siraj al-munir (ff. 1-66) is a 17th century work by Mu?ammad Sharif ibn Shams al-Din Mu?ammad. The second work (ff. 67-130) is a collection of poems by Hadi ibn Mahdi Sabzavari (b. 1797 or 8). The title of the second work, as given in the manuscript, is Divan-i ta ?lifat va ghazaliyyat-i afkar-i abkar-i fakhr al-?arifin jinab-i ?aji Mulla Hadi-yi Sabzavari al-mutikhalli? bi Asrar, which translates to "The anthology of the compositions and sonnets of the unprecedented ideas of the glory of Gnostics, his grace the pilgrim Mulla Hadi of Sabzavar, with the nom-de-plume 'Mysteries'." The scribe has written some dedicatory lines to the Qajar prince Amid al-Dawlah (66a).
    * ff. 1b-65a: The luminous light beams. * ff. 1b-4b: Table of contents. * ff. 4b-8a: The first flash: courtesy. * ff. 8a-11a: The second flash: shame. * ff. 11a-13b: The third flash: restraint. * ff. 13b-16a: The fourth flash: justice. * ff. 16a-19a: The fifth flash: benevolence. * ff. 19a-22b: The sixth flash: patience. * ff. 22b-26b: The seventh flash: love. * ff. 26b-29b: The eighth flash: kindness. * ff. 29b-32b: The ninth flash: generosity. * ff. 32b-37b: The tenth flash: bravery. * ff. 37b-41a: The eleventh flash: conversation. * ff. 41a-45a: The twelfth flash: reversal of fortune. * ff. 45a-47b: The thirteenth flash: silence. * ff. 47b-50b: The fourteenth flash: the ability to live without. * ff. 50b-52a: The fifteenth flash: coveting. * ff. 52a-54a: The sixteenth flash: youngmanliness (chivalry). * ff. 54a-56b: The seventeenth flash: foresight. * ff. 56b-59a: The eighteenth flash: oppression. * ff. 59a-61b: The nineteenth flash: fraud. * ff. 61b-64b: The twentieth flash: jealousy. * ff. 64b-65a: Closing. * ff. 66a-66b: Dedication. * ff. 67a-130a: The anthology of Sabzavari.
    Layout: Average 15 lines of text per page.
    Binding: Soft black leather, blind stamped.
    Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink on blue paper, with headings, some names, verse markers, and some punctuation in red. Title of second work on fore-edge.
  - 11 ?iya? al-?amir The glow of comprehension., 1730 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    Author: Mullá ?Ali.
    Scribe: ShAmlu, Murta?á Quli.
    Physical Description: 56 leaves: paper; 183 x 109 mm. bound to 183 x 109 mm.
    Origin: Persia.
    Scope and Content Note Mathematical treatise covering basic arithmetic functions, including radicals, fractions, functions and uses, sample problems, and basic geometry. The target audience is probably those who use the information for practical matters, specifically small business accounting. For example, the first two sample problems deal with calculating wages; the third with buying produce; and the fourth and the fifth with the volume of water in cisterns.
    * ff. 1b-3a: Opening. * ff. 3a-4b: Addition. * ff. 4b-5a: Halving. * ff. 5a-6a: Subtractions. * ff. 6a-15a: Multiplications. * ff. 15a-17b: Divisions. * ff. 17b-23b: Radicals. * ff. 23b-28b: Fractions. * ff. 28b-29a: Adding fractions. * ff. 29a-30a: Halving fractions. * ff. 30a-32b: Multiplying fractions. * ff. 32b-41a: Dividing fractions and other points. * ff. 41a-43a: Uses (accounting). * ff. 43a-49a: Sample problems. * ff. 49a-56b: Geometry (measuring area).
    Layout: Average 9 lines of text per page.
    Binding: Soft red morocco.
    Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, with charts, numbers, and headings in red. Staining and damage at the bottom right fore-edge; occasional marginalia. Extended title on the spine.
  - 12 [Prayer book]., [ca. 18--?] (Box 2, Folder 9)
    Physical Description: 135 leaves: paper; 133 x 98 mm. bound to 135 x 103 mm.
    Origin: Iran.
    Scope and Content Note Shiite prayer book of Koran verses, in addition to Arabic prayers accompanying instructions in Persian.
    * ff. 1b: Chapter 1 and 117 of the Koran (al-IkhlA? & al-Fati?a). * ff. 2a-11b: The prayer of Kumayl. * ff. 11b-15a: The prayer of "surrendering abundantly" (Tasliman Kathiran). * ff. 15a-19a: The prayer of "those who pardon" (al-Ra?imin). * ff. 19a-20a: The prayer of ending a visitation to the prophet and his family. * ff. 20a-32a: The prayer of twelve Imams by Na?ir al-Din al-?usi. * ff. 32a-33a: The prayer of Ali in the bed (Firash). * ff. 33b: The prayer after the Morning Prayer. * ff. 34a: The prayer after praising Fa?ima al-Zahra?. * ff. 34b: The prayer for after every required Prayer (namaz). * ff. 34b-35a: After the Morning Prayer. * ff. 35a-36a: After the Noon Prayer. * ff. 36a-37a: After the Afternoon Prayer. * ff. 37a-37b: After the Sunset Prayer. * ff. 37b-39a: Also after the Sunset Prayer. * ff. 39a-40a: Prayers to be recited after the required Prayers during holy months. * ff. 40a-42b: Prayer for the pre-dawn (sa?ar) during Rama?an. * ff. 42b-46a: Prayer for the night of the nineteenth of Rama?an. * ff. 46a-47b: Prayer for the night of the twenty-first of the same month. * ff. 47b-49a: Prayers for the festival of breaking the fast (?d al-fi?r). * ff. 49a-60a: Prayers for the pilgrimage to great shrines. * ff. 60a-64b: Prayer for the tenth of Mu?arram. * ff. 64b-67a: How to visit Imam al-Ri?a. * ff. 67a-91a: Prayers for solving problems. * ff. 91a-94a: The prayer for deflecting adversity. * ff. 94a-: The prayer of the tens (?asharat). * ff. 101a-119a: The prayer of the small coat of mail (jawshan-i ?aghir). * ff. 119b-121a: Prayers (in a different hand). * ff. 121a-135: Blank.
    Layout: Average of 15 lines of text per page.
    Script: Naskh (Arabic) and nasta? liq. (Persian).
    Binding: Brown leather, blind stamped.
    Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink on blue, yellow, green, or pink paper, with headings and underlines in red.
  - 13 A?adith Hadiths., [between 1514 and 1558] (Box 3, Folder 1)
    Author: Qummi, Mu?ammad ibn A?mad, 10th/11th cent.
    Scribe: Mashhadi, Abu ?alib ibn Abu al-Fat? al-?usayni.
    Physical Description: 58 leaves: paper, ill.; 199 x 123 mm. bound to 208 x 140 mm.
    Origin: [Persia].
    Scope and Content Note Illuminated collection of Shiite Hadiths, or sayings of holy figures, translated into Persian. Mashhadi, the compiler, translator and calligrapher of the manuscript, writes that it was created for non-Arabic readers in ?afawid Persia. The major, but not exclusive source for selections is the work of 9th century scholar Mu?ammad ibn A?mad Qummi. The manuscript is dedicated to Shah ?ahmasb ?afawid (r. 1524-1576).
    * ff. 1b-4a: Opening. * ff. 4a-7b: First hadith. * ff. 7b-11a: Second hadith. * ff. 11a-13a: Third hadith. * ff. 13a-15a: Fourth hadith. * ff. 15a-16a: Fifth hadith. * ff. 16a-17b: Sixth hadith. * ff. 18a-19b: Seventh hadith. * ff. 19b-20b: Eighth hadith. * ff. 20b-22b: Ninth hadith. * ff. 22b-25a: Tenth hadith. * ff. 25a-26a: Eleventh hadith. * ff. 26a-27b:Twelfth hadith. * ff. 27b-29a:Thirteenth hadith. * ff. 29a-31b: Fourteenth hadith. * ff. 31b-32b: First story. * ff. 32b-37b: Second story. * ff. 37b-39a: Third story. * ff. 39a-40b: Fourth story. * ff. 40b-42b: Twelve hadiths of Moses. * ff. 43a: blank. * ff. 43b-58a: Prayer and closing.
    Layout: Average of 11 lines of text per page.
    Script: Naskh; from 40b-42b Arabic text in naskh, Persian text in nasta? liq.
    Decoration: Illuminated throughout.
    Binding: Black lacquer boards, painted in gold and black, with a red leather spine.
    Additional description: Text in black, red, green, and blue, framed a thin green, gold, red, white, and blue decorative border.
    Text in Persian and Arabic.
  - 14 Kitab-i ?ibb-i ?akim-i Ma?i mawsum bih si bakhiyah The medical book of the former sage known as the thirty stitches., 1866. (Box 3, Folder 2)
    Author: [Shamlu, Murta?á Quli].
    Scribe: ?imni.
    Physical Description: 66 leaves: paper; 182 x 106 mm. bound to 186 x 112 mm.